Praneet Vayalali

GRADUATE RESEARCH ASSISTANT

Center for Mobility with Vertical Lift, Rensselaer Polytechnic Institute, Troy, New York

□+1 (508) 446-4583 | ■ vayalalipraneet@gmail.com | ■ vayalp@rpi.edu | # Homepage | LinkedIn | Google Scholar

Summary .

A highly motivated PhD candidate with a passion for aviation pursuing research in the field of flight dynamics and control with focus on fault tolerant control on VTOL aircraft. Current work focuses on utilizing redundant control effectors for damage tolerance on VTOL aircraft by applying modern control design techniques.

Education ____

Ph.D. in Aeronautical Engineering

RENSSELAER POLYTECHNIC INSTITUTE (RPI), GPA - 3.83/4

Master of Technology in Aerospace Engineering

INDIAN INSTITUTE OF TECHNOLOGY KANPUR (IIT K), GPA - 9.25/10

Bachelor of Technology in Aerospace Engineering

AMRITA SCHOOL OF ENGINEERING (ASE), GPA - 8.91/10

Aug. 2016 - July 2021

Troy, NY, USA

July 2014 - July 2016

Kanpur, India

uly 2009 - Juno 2013

Coimbatore, India

Technical Skills ___

Softwares RPI GenHel derivative model, MATLAB/SIMULINK, CONDUIT, CIFER, LabView, Ansys Fluent, Abaqus, Hyperworks

Languages C++, Python

General Git, Linux, Microsoft Office Suite, Latex

Research Experience _____

Post-Damage Reconfiguration for Rotorcraft with Control Redundancy

Aug. 2016 - Current

Ph.D. Dissertation, Advisor - Dr. Farhan Gandhi

RPI, NY, USA

- Examine adaptive and robust fly-by-wire flight control strategies that can tolerate damage/degradation in various control effectors to enable safe flight on VTOL aircraft with control redundancy.
- Perform nonlinear flight simulation and handling qualities (ADS-33E) based analysis on the use of various control allocation and modern control design techniques on a UH-60 Black Hawk and derivative compound helicopter platforms.

Post-Failure Control Reconfiguration on a High-Speed Lift-Offset Coaxial Helicopter

Aug. 2019 - Current

RESEARCH PROJECT, ADVISOR - DR. FARHAN GANDHI

RPI, NY, USA

- Work with a team of two to investigate the potential for fault compensation in flight for a lift-offset coaxial helicopter by examining the interchangeability of controls at different points within the flight envelope, thereby identifying allowable fault cases for the vehicle.
- Helped with the development of an elastic blade coaxial-pusher helicopter trim model based on the X2 TechnologyTM demonstrator which was then used to explore trim control variation in different flight regimes.

Frequency Domain Based System Identification of a Small-Sized RUAV

May 2015 - Jul. 2016

MASTER'S THESIS, ADVISOR - DR. A. ABHISHEK

IIT Kanpur, India

- Characterized a fully instrumented small-size rotary-wing unmanned aerial vehicle (RUAV) using a frequency domain based experimental system identification technique.
- Flight test of a 1 kg class RUAV was conducted and its responses were recorded. The closed-loop responses were analyzed to extract a bareairframe 6-DOF linear flight dynamics state space model of the aircraft for hover flight condition. This was followed up by flight test validation.

Axial Compressive Testing of Single Carbon Fibers

Aug. 2013 - Jul. 2014

RESEARCH PROJECT, ADVISORS - DR. C.S. UPADHYAY & DR. P.M. MOHITE

IIT Kanpur, India

• Conducted over 500 axial recoil tests on single carbon fibers of varying lengths and diameters (order of 10 microns) in order to determine the compressive strength of the fiber. This experimental data was then used to statistically model the scattering in strength due to various parameters.

Detection of Cracks in a Wind Turbine Blade using Modal Analysis

Aug. 2013 - Jul. 2014

BACHELOR'S THESIS, ADVISORS - DR. LAXMAN VAITLA & DR. V.L. SATHEESH (NATIONAL AEROSPACE LABORATORIES)

ASE, India

- Examined frequency response of non-rotating GFRP (Glass Fiber Reinforced Plastic) rectangular beams using finite element analysis for varying delamination sizes and positions.
- Conducted sinusoidal sweep experimental tests on GFRP beams to validate the simulation results.
- Performed modal analysis (using finite element method) on rotating composite beams to simulate rotating wind turbine blades.

Projects.

Backstepping Control for a Variable-RPM Quadrotor Aircraft

Jan. 2019 - May 2019

NONLINEAR CONTROL SYSTEMS COURSE PROJECT

RPI, NY, USA

- Demonstrated the applicability of backstepping control design to a hobbyist scale quadrotor vehicle.
- Examined the performance of a backstepping feedback controller in comparison to a PID controller on the quadrotor.

Extreme Altitude Mountain Rescue Vehicle

Jan. 2019 - May 2019

THE VERTICAL FLIGHT SOCIETY'S 36TH ANNUAL STUDENT DESIGN COMPETITION

RPI, NY, USA

- Proposed a synchropter as a VTOL aircraft design capable of search and rescue missions at the summit of Mt Everest, where only one helicopter has ever landed and taken off again.
- Developed a 6-DOF flight dynamics model and analyzed the autonomous dynamics of the proposed rotorcraft design. Design constraints include freezing temperatures, thin air and hostile weather conditions with degraded visual environment all contribute to making rescue work in high-altitude environments particularly dangerous or impossible.
- · Won third place in the graduate category the vertical flight society's 36th annual student design competition.

Power Optimization for UH-60 Black Hawk in Cruise using Variable RPM and Stabilator

Sept. 2017 - Dec. 2017

INDEPENDENT STUDY FOR ADVANCED DESIGN OPTIMIZATION COURSE

RPI, NY, USA

• Optimized power using the main rotor speed and stabilator pitch incidence as design variables on a physics-based UH-60 Black Hawk helicopter simulation model at a cruise speed of 140 knots.

Controller Design for a Quadrotor UAV

Jan. 2017 - May 2017

HELICOPTER DESIGN COURSE PROJECT

RPI, NY, USA

- Nonlinear flight simulation model with PID and LQR controllers were developed for a 2 kg quadrotor helicopter and their performance was compared in simulation.
- Compared control schemes using controller gains tuned for the hover flight condition and flown for single waypoint and multiple waypoint trajectories.

Design of V/STOL Air Taxi

Dec. 2014 - May 2015

AIAA FOUNDATION GRADUATE TEAM AIRCRAFT DESIGN COMPETITION

IIT Kanpur, India

- Worked with a team of seven to propose a design for an air taxi system that operates out of confined urban areas requiring vertical and short takeoff and landing capability.
- Involved in the design of a ducted rotor system for the V/STOL aircraft with consideration of noise and safety.

Journal Articles

- Vayalali, P., McKay, M., Gandhi, F., "Redistributed Pseudoinverse Control Allocation for Actuator Failure on a High-Speed Compound Helicopter," Journal of American Helicopter Society, Submitted (Under Review), November 2020.
- Vayalali, P., McKay, M., Krishnamurthi, J., Gandhi, F., "Fault-Tolerant Control on a UH-60 Black Hawk Helicopter using Horizontal Stabilator," CEAS Aeronautical Journal, Vol. 12(1), Jan 2021, pp. 13-27, DOI:10.1007/s13272-020-00476-5.
- **Vayalali, P.**, McKay, M., Krishnamurthi, J., Gandhi, F., "Horizontal Stabilator Utilization for Post Swashplate Failure Operation on a UH-60 Black Hawk Helicopter," Journal of the American Helicopter Society, Vol. 65, April 2020, pp. 1–13(13), DOI:10.4050/JAHS.65.022009.

Conference Proceedings L

- Vayalali, P., McKay, M., Gandhi, F., "Fault-Tolerant Control Allocation on a Compound Helicopter in Cruise," Proceedings of the Vertical Flight Society 77th Annual Forum, West Palm Beach, FL, 11-13 May 2021 (to be presented).
- McKay, M., **Vayalali, P.**, Gandhi, F., "Redistributed Control Allocation for Flight Control Failure on a Coaxial Helicopter," Proceedings of the Vertical Flight Society 77th Annual Forum, West Palm Beach, FL, 11-13 May 2021 (to be presented).
- Vayalali, P., McKay, M., Gandhi, F., "Redistributed Pseudoinverse Control Allocation for Actuator Failure on a Compound Helicopter," Proceedings of the Vertical Flight Society 76th Annual Forum, Virtual, 6-8 Oct 2020.
- McKay, M., **Vayalali, P.**, Gandhi, F., "Post-Failure Control Reconfiguration for a Lift-Offset Coaxial Helicopter," Proceedings of the Vertical Flight Society 76th Annual Forum, Virtual, 6-8 Oct 2020.
- Vayalali, P., McKay, M., Krishnamurthi, J., Gandhi, F., "Robust Use of Horizontal Stabilator in Feedback Control on a UH-60 Black Hawk," Proceedings of the Vertical Flight Society 75th Annual Forum, Philadelphia, PA, 13-17 May 2019.

• Vayalali, P., McKay, M., Krishnamurthi, J., Gandhi, F., "Swashplate Actuator Failure Compensation for UH-60 Black Hawk in Cruise Using Horizontal Stabilator," Proceedings of the 74th American Helicopter Society Annual Forum, Phoenix, AZ, 7-10 May 2018.

Relevant Courses

VFS Forum 76 Short Course on EVTOL Design Nonlinear Control Systems Helicopter Design Multivariable/Robust Control Systems Systems Analysis Techniques Advanced Design Optimization Intro to Machine Learning Rotorcraft Performance, Stability and Control Intro to Virtual Instrumentation

Honors & Awards

2018	Third Place, The Vertical Flight Society's 36th Annual Student Design Competition	Virginia, USA
2017	Runner-up, The American Helicopter Society Northeast Region Robert L. Lichten Award Competition	Stratford, USA
2012	Second Place, RC aircraft modeling event as a part of techfest of Amrita School of Engineering	Coimbatore, India
2010	First Place, SAE College level Aero Modeling Tier I event	Coimbatore, India

Professional Societies _____

Vertical Flight Society (VFS)

2016 - Current

Fairfax, VA, USA

- President, RPI student chapter (2020-2021)
- Senior Student Volunteer (SSV), one of the 8 SSVs responsible for all A/V at VFS Forum 76 Virtual (2020)
- Student Volunteer at Forum 73 (2017), Forum 74 (2018) & Forum 75 (2019)

American Institute of Aeronautics and Astronautics (AIAA)

2014 - Current

STUDENT MEMBER

STUDENT MEMBER

Reston, VA, USA

• Participated in the AIAA Foundation Graduate team Aircraft Design Competition (2015)